specifically whether the פסוק pasuk is repeated in צו, Tzav, because it’s
in ויקרא Vayikra and then in צו. Tzav. Thank you. So רב
Rav says that if it’s repeated, it’s מעכב, me'akev, and if it’s
not repeated, it’s not מעכב, me'akev, which is a pretty general principle.
And now we are going to see whether this really works. So
yesterday we discussed the issue of הגשה, hagashah, and that is not
מעכב, me'akev, but it’s repeated. And we said that the reason it’s
repeated is to tell you exactly where you do the הגשה. hagashah.
So now we continue again, today’s דף daf is דף כ, daf
chaf, we pick up יט עמוד ב, yod tet amud bet, two
lines from bottom. And the camera... oh okay, sorry.
Every day it’s a little adjustment. All right. מתקיף ליה רב הונא,
Matkif lei Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna asked,
הרי מלח, harei melach, so salt, right, when we learned that in
the משנה mishnah that it wasn’t מעכב, me'akev, Michael was shocked because,
you know, the תורה Torah says לא תשבית מלח ברית אלהיך מעל
מנחתך. lo tashbit melach berit elokecha me'al minchatecha. So the גמרא Gemara
here is going to ask specifically about salt. דלא תנא ביה קרא,
delo tana bei kra, it’s not repeated, the idea of salt actually
interestingly appears in ויקרא Vayikra not in צו, Tzav, which goes against
the general theory that I wrote about, I mean it’s not my
חידוש, chiddush, you know, it’s the... that צו Tzav is basically the
focus on... צו Tzav is basically repetition of ויקרא, Vayikra, but a
repetition from the perspective of the כהנים, Kohanim, whereas ויקרא Vayikra is
from the perspective of the one who brings the קרבן. korban. צו
Tzav opens with צו את אהרן, Tzav et Aharon, ויקרא אל משה...
Vayikra el Moshe... דבר אל בני ישראל לאמר, Daber el bnei yisrael
lemor, ויקרא Vayikra opens with דבר אל בני ישראל לאמר. Daber el
bnei yisrael lemor. So it is interesting though that the whole idea
that you must have salt on all of your קרבנות korbanot is
in ויקרא Vayikra and not in צו. Tzav. That doesn’t exactly fit
that pattern. But be that as it may, it’s not repeated,
okay, הרי מלח, harei melach, דלא תנא ביה קרא, delo tana bei
kra, the תורה Torah did not repeat it,
and
it’s מעכב me'akev in
it. It’s funny that
the
גמרא Gemara assumes it’s מעכב me'akev against the
משנה, mishnah, starting with the ברייתא, braita, starting with a ברייתא braita
and it’s going to seem in a minute that the גמרא Gemara
is going
to
actually seems more you know intuitively persuaded by the ברייתא. braita. If
it says ברית מלח עולם berit melach olam it should be מעכב.
me'akev. But now it’s turning it around and saying, ah, but רב,
Rav, you said that the only way something is מעכב me'akev is
if it’s repeated. And this is not repeated. So what are you
going to do? So we’ll see what the answer is. But before
we get to that, well you know we’ll see what the answer
is and then we’ll go back and understand the exact פסוק pasuk
that was originally quoted.
Yes. Good question, but could you ask how do you know that
כהונה kehunah is מעכב? me'akev?
That is an interesting question. I mean it’s true in a way
that the גמרא, Gemara, I mean within this דרשה drasha because in
a way, you know, it said before how do you know where
you need כהונה? kehunah? If it says כהן kohen and אצבע etzba
or ימין yamin and אצבע etzba and these types of things. Right.
What? Maybe it doesn’t say תורה Torah or חוקה. chukah.
Right. So you know, it’s a good point.
I mean it’s repeated a hundred times. Right.
I think look, the גמרא Gemara and we’ll see this in a
minute like here too, I mean for God’s sake, if it says
ברית עולם, berit olam, so isn’t that a good enough explanation why
it’s מעכב? me'akev? So תוספות Tosafot explains that the גמרא Gemara initially
assumed that since רב Rav made this statement like when it comes
to מנחה mincha if it’s repeated it’s מעכב, me'akev, if it’s not
it’s not, it sounded to the גמרא Gemara like it’s only in
issue of it being repeated and there’s no other way to know
it. So we already because you could really ask what’s the גמרא
Gemara getting on רב Rav’s back? I mean isn’t this a general
principle of things are repeated they are מעכב, me'akev, if not, not?
So the answer is is that yes, but normally it’s one of
the ways we know it’s מעכב. me'akev. We also know sometimes because
of חוק chok it’s מעכב, me'akev, or תורה Torah it’s מעכב, me'akev,
you know, or ת tav or other types of things. So what
the גמרא, Gemara, so תוספות Tosafot already points this out, the גמרא
Gemara sort of thought that רב Rav was saying by מנחה mincha
the only way it’s מעכב me'akev is if it’s repeated. So I
think that sort of answers your question as well. Of course we
know other things are מעכב. me'akev. We’ve already had these principles around.
But it’s within the narrow context of מנחה mincha that we were
asking is this really the only way that we know it. And
now the גמרא Gemara is about to adjust that in a minute
as we will see. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, אמר רב
יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, רב כתנא דידן סבירא ליה. Rav ketanna didan
sevira lei. Now notice the first answer is actually even though it
says ברית עולם, berit olam, you know, we have our משנה. mishnah.
That it's not מעכב. me'akev. So אי הכי נמי ein hachi nami
by a מנחה Mincha I don't care how many times it says
ברית עולם, brit olam, it is not מעכב. me'akev. Okay, דאמר, d'amar,
and our משנה Mishnah says, לא מלח כשרה. lo malach kesheira. If
you didn't do מליחה, melicha, it's כשרה. kesheira. So you're right, מלח
melach would not be מעכב me'akev according to רב Rav even though
the תורה Torah calls it a ברית עולם. brit olam. אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back, אי הכי לא
יצק נמי לא יצק כלל? ei hachi lo yetzak nami lo yetzak
klal? So אביי Abaye said one minute, you cannot say that there
really is a תנא tana that says that without מלח salt it's
כשר kosher because let's go to the other phrase in the משנה.
Mishnah. If you don't do יציקה yetziqa it's כשר. kosher. Now again,
פשט pshat of that משנה Mishnah means exactly what it says. But
we've established, we sort of came with the assumption that יציקה yetziqa
is מעכב, me'akev, the גמרא Gemara said it earlier although it never
even actually quoted פסוקים p-sukim about that. And we reinterpreted it to
mean that if you didn't do it with a כהן Kohen but
you did it with a זר. Zar. So once we've interpreted יציקה
yetziqa to mean not really that it's not מעכב, me'akev, but that
you can do it with a זר. Zar. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so let's take a look. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so- so
נמי לא יצק כלל, nami lo yetzak klal, would you really say
that if you don't do יציקה yetziqa it's כשר? kosher? אלא, Ela,
how do we reinterpret that line of the משנה? Mishnah? לא יצק
כהן אלא זר. Lo yetzak Kohen ela Zar. A כהן Kohen didn't
do it, it was done by a non-כהן. Kohen. So therefore, once
that's what לא יצק lo yetzak means in the משנה, Mishnah, we
should interpret לא מלח lo malach the same way. For God's sake,
if the תורה Torah says ברית מלח עולם, brit melach olam, let's
interpret לא מלח lo malach not to mean you really didn't do
the מליחה, melicha, it means a non-כהן Kohen did the מליחה. melicha.
הכא נמי, Hacha nami, so let's say as well, לא מלח כהן
אלא זר. lo malach Kohen ela Zar. It means a non-כהן. Kohen.
Now again, notice how fascinating this is. You got פשט pshat in
the משנה Mishnah that a מליחה melicha is not מעכב. me'akev. You
have it consistent with the position of רב. Rav. But the גמרא
Gemara starts with the assumption that מליחה melicha is מעכב, me'akev, quotes
a ברייתא, braita, tries to defend רב Rav with the משנה Mishnah
and says, oh you can't read that משנה כפשוטו. Mishnah k-p-shuto. So
it really shows you know the גמרא Gemara has an almost a-priori
bias to assume that מליחה melicha is מעכב me'akev presumably based on
the פסוק pasuk that it's called ברית עולם brit olam and it
does not want to read the משנה כפשוטו. Mishnah k-p-shuto. So let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara response to this is. אמר ליה, Amar
lei,
so he says back to him, אמר ליה, Amar lei, וכי תעלה
על דעתך שזר קרב לגבי מזבח? ve-chi ta'aleh al da'at-cha she-zar kareiv
l-gabei mizbeach?
You can't read the משנה Mishnah that way that a non-כהן Kohen
can do the מליחה. melicha. How could we think that a non-כהן
Kohen could get to the top of the מזבח? mizbeach? Because where
do you do the מליחה? melicha? You do the מליחה melicha on
the קומץ kometz right before you burn it, so presumably you're up
there by the fire, top of the מזבח, mizbeach, and you're doing
the מליחה. melicha. Can you think that we would ever allow that?
Now all of a sudden the ראשונים Rishonim ask, I don't understand.
It might be an affront, it might be he's even over on
an איסור, issur, but that doesn't get to the core question of
if he did do that and he did the מליחה, melicha, is
it כשר kosher or not? Right? So how can you say that
the משנה Mishnah can't mean a non-כהן Kohen can do the מליחה?
melicha? Maybe it means exactly that, that a non-כהן Kohen can do
the מליחה melicha and even though we normally wouldn't allow it, it
doesn't mean that it's not כשר. kosher. So the שיטה מקובצת Shita
Mekubetzet asks this question and he basically answers that no, what the
גמרא Gemara really means is not the affront of a non-כהן Kohen
going to the מזבח. mizbeach. What it really means is, remember we
said before that it says you bring it to the כהן Kohen
and then the כהן Kohen does the קמיצה kmitsa and we said
מקמיצה ואילך מצות כהונה. mi-kmitsa ve-eilach mitzvat kehuna. So what it really
means to say is not because he's at the מזבח. mizbeach. What
it really means is this is a stage that's after קמיצה. kmitsa.
So how could anybody suggest a post-קמיצה kmitsa stage is done by
a non-כהן, Kohen, right? That's never come up before. When we've ever
discussed non-כהנים, kohanim, it's always been at an earlier stage prior to
the handoff. But once there's the handoff, then the- then it's all
the realm of the כהנים. kohanim. Okay, so that's the way the
שיטה Shita reads it. I'm not sure it's exactly פשט pshat of
the line, but it is fascinating that the גמרא Gemara like says,
oh no no no, we- it's impossible to even imagine a non-כהן
Kohen doing it. But you know, we also imagine the unimaginable and
ask theoretical questions. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is forced to admit that
פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah about if you don't do the
מליחה melicha can't be a non-כהן, Kohen, that's inconceivable. It's forced to
admit that פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah is the פשט. pshat.
That according to the משנה, Mishnah, if you don't do מליחה melicha
it's כשר. kosher. So therefore it says רב Rav who says that
if you don't repeat it, it's not מעכב me'akev would just be
the משנה Mishnah that אי הכי נמי ein hachi nami salt is
not מעכב. me'akev. Okay, let's see how the גמרא Gemara concludes. ואיבעית
אימא, V-iba'it eima, and if you want I can say רב Rav
also says that doing the מלח melach is מעכב. me'akev. So ואיבעית
אימא כיון דכתיב ביה ברית כמאן דתנא ביה קרא דמי. v-iba'it eima
keivan di-chtiva beih brit k-man di-tna beih kra dami.
So
since it says ברית, brit, it's like the פסוק pasuk repeated it,
like we always say. It says חוק, chok, it says יהיה, yihiye,
it says ברית, briss, you don't need it to repeat. So here
by the way is exactly the point that תוספות Tosafot made and
that I cited before in response to דוב, Dov, which is that
the גמרא Gemara is assuming that when רב Rav says it has
to repeat, he means it extremely narrowly. Because we already know a
general principle that things need to be repeated by קרבנות מנחות. korbanot
menachot. So we thought he meant that that's the only way things
are מעכב. me'akev. So then we said well what about salt? And
then in the end it answers either salt isn't מעכב me'akev or
yes you don't really need it to be repeated, ברית briss also
counts like we normally assume. But what is again amazing about this
גמרא Gemara is it starts against the משנה, Mishnah, takes it so
much for granted that salt is מעכב, me'akev, presumably based on the
פסוק pasuk that it's called ברית עולם brit olam and it does
not want to read the משנה כפשוטו. Mishnah k-p-shuto. presumably because the
תורה Torah calls it a ברית עולם, bris olam, right? And therefore
but still can't conceive that how does it sit into the system
of רב? Rav? Until it admits that רב Rav would also be
influenced by the phrase ברית עולם. bris olam. So clearly the inclination
of גמרא, Gemara, it's worth noting this, is that the משנה Mishna
says יציקה's yetzika not מעכב ma'akeiv and מלח melach is not מעכב
ma'akeiv and because of the גמרא's Gemara not even evidence against it,
but assumptions against it, we now say that יציקה yetzika really means
that it doesn't have to be done by the כהן, Kohein, but
it is מעכב, ma'akeiv, and מלח melach is מעכב, ma'akeiv, and we
basically פסקן pasken against the משנה. Mishna. Okay, now the question is,
well, okay, so far
based on the ברייתא, braisa, based on a ברייתא.
braisa. But never that גמרא Gemara even said like, you know, it's
clear that it's not like the ברייתא braisa is more weighty from
a technical point of view. The גמרא's Gemara just, you know, the
גמרא's Gemara just sort of, you know, assumes the ברייתא's braisa correct
in this case. Okay, so now let's take a look at whether
this פסוק pasuk was actually repeated or not. Okay. ולא תנא ביה
קרא, V'lo tana bei kra, did the תורה Torah not repeat itself,
but when it comes to salt, meaning your whole question was it
didn't repeat itself and you had an answer ברית, bris, but what
do you mean, the תורה Torah did repeat itself by salt. How
do you know? והא כתיב, V'hachasiv, the פסוק pasuk says וכל קרבן
מנחתך במלח תמלח, v'chol korban minchascha b'melach timlach, and all of the
קרבן korban of your and all of your מנחה mincha קרבנות korbanos
you should salt it with salt. Now where is it repeating itself?
Until now repeating itself has meant it says it once in ויקרא
Vayikra and another time in צו. Tzav. Here it does not say
it another time in צו. Tzav. So you could say the repeating
itself is, it says it here in ויקרא, Vayikra, וכל קרבן מנחתך
במלח תמלח, v'chol korban minchascha b'melach timlach, and the פסוק pasuk we
quoted at the bottom of י"ט עמוד ב' yud tes amud beis
was ברית מלח עולם. bris melach olam. That was the פסוק pasuk
we started with. So there it's repeating itself. That sounds like it.
You've quoted one פסוק, pasuk, I'll quote you another פסוק. pasuk. The
problem is that ברית מלח עולם bris melach olam is said at
the end of קרח Korach and it refers to the מתנות matnos
of the כהונה. kehuna. If you give me hand me the תנ"ך,
Tanakh, it uses salt as like the symbol of what a covenant
is, but it's not actually saying there that there is a covenant
with the salt. It's sort of taking it for granted. It says
in במדבר, Bamidbar, right, everybody knows in קרח Korach there after the
whole כהונה kehuna was challenged, the תורה Torah repeats at the end
of קרח, Korach, you know, what the כהנים Kohanim are entitled to.
So it says
like this, it says,
so it gives all the list of what the כהן Kohein gets,
אך בכור שור ובכור כשב ובכור עז לא תפדה, ach bechor shor
v'chor kesev v'chor ez lo tifdeh, כל תרומת הקדשים אשר ירימו בני
ישראל לה' נתתי לך ולבניך ולבנתיך אתך לחק עולם ברית מלח עולם
היא לפני ה' לך ולזרעך אתך. kol trumas hakodashim asher yarimu bnei
yisrael l'Hashem nasati lcha u'lvanecha u'lvnotcha itcha l'chok olam, bris melach olam
hi lifnei Hashem lcha u'lzarcha itcha. So it's basically the way, you
know, it's an eternal covenant that you get these gifts of the
כהונה, kehuna, which is why the ברייתא braisa compared the salt to
the כהונה. kehuna. The same way that you know you always need
כהנים, Kohanim, you always need salt because in the פסוק pasuk it's
talking about the promise to the כהנים. Kohanim. So, you know, it's
hard to say that such a תנא ביה tana bei what?
What does it even mean there?
ברית מלח עולם? bris melach olam? Yeah, well, okay, it could be,
you're right, is it just because the תורה Torah said in ויקרא
Vayikra that, you know, that this is my ברית bris with the
salt or therefore we know that this is a symbol of ברית
bris or it could also be that's the way you preserve things
is you put them in salt, you know, so maybe a covenant
of salt means like a covenant that's meant to last and everlasting,
I don't know, but the גמרא Gemara understands that it means that
just like the ברית bris of salt back in the beginning of
ויקרא Vayikra that that has to always be with the קרבנות. korbanos.
Of course the irony is, is that in the פסוק pasuk the
ברית bris of salt is the paradigm and it's being applied to
the כהונה. kehuna. The גמרא Gemara that we just read reversed it.
גמרא Gemara says כשם שאפשר לקרבנו בלא כהונה כך אפשר לקרבנו בלא
מלח. k'sheim she'efshar l'korbano blo kehuna, kach efshar l'korbano blo melach. So
the כהונה's kehuna taken more for granted and the salt is more
of the חידוש. chiddush. Be that as it may, it's a funny
example of תנא ביה קרא tana bei kra because this פסוק pasuk
is not saying you need salt. It's sort of just drawing on
that idea. So רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam switched the גרסא girsa back
in the previous גמרא Gemara and he says we were not using
the פסוק pasuk of קרח. Korach. It was not the גרסא girsa
of ברית מלח עולם, bris melach olam, actually in ויקרא Vayikra itself
it says ברית bris by the salt twice. And let me just
find the פסוק pasuk there in ויקרא. Vayikra. What? It's the next
פסוק? pasuk? What is it? ולא תשבית מלח ברית אלהיך מעל מנחתך.
V'lo
tashbis
melach bris elokeicha mei'al minchasecha. Right. על כל קרבנך תקריב מלח. Al
kol korbancha takriv melach. Right, so it says it twice. It says
וכל קרבן מנחתך במלח תמלח, v'chol korban minchascha b'melach timlach, which is
what we just quoted, and then it says
ולא תשבית מלח ברית אלהיך מעל מנחתך, v'lo tashbis melach bris elokeicha
mei'al minchasecha, על כל קרבנך תקריב מלח. al kol korbancha takriv melach.
So רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that back here where it says
ברית bris it was really saying ברית מלח, bris melach, you know,
מלח ברית אלהיך melach bris elokeicha was the פסוק pasuk it meant
to quote, not the פסוק pasuk from קרח. Korach. Okay, so whether
he's right or not it is funny that that's called here תנא
ביה קרא tana bei kra and it's easier to understand תנא ביה
קרא tana bei kra that even in those פסוקים pesukim in ויקרא
Vayikra it repeats it more than once. The idea that you must
have the salt. So now the גמרא's Gemara saying like this, why
did you make give you know why did you make such a
big deal of the fact that the תורה Torah did not repeat
it, doesn't it say וכל קרבן מנחתך במלח תמלח, v'chol korban minchascha
b'melach timlach, which is it's just repeating it either it's from what
you have in קרח Korach or what you have in the next
part of the פסוק pasuk by the salt itself. It does. It
does repeat it. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא ha-hu miba-ye lei l'ched-tanya that you need it
for what we taught in the ברייתא. braitah. And now we're going
to tell you some of the details of the מלח. melach. Now
notice by the way the structure of what the גמרא Gemara is
doing. Under the framework
of explaining what is and is not מעכב me-akev in the משנה
Mishnah and רב's Rav principle that it have to repeat and we
have a whole list of things that are not מעכב, me-akev, on
the one hand we're showing where we know they're not
מעכב, me-akev, or re-interpreting something like the salt and the סיפא, sifa,
and on the other hand once we're bringing in the פסוקים psukim
where and we're saying oh but isn't this a repetition? It becomes
also an opportunity to discuss some of the details of those things.
So in the process we've learned the details of הגשה, hagashah, now
we're going to learn some of the details of מלח. melach. So
by the end of going through this we're going to understand not
only how these things are not מעכב, me-akev, but some of the
ways in which these things are done. Okay, says גמרא Gemara here,
I'm going to tell you why you needed the repetition by the
salt. Okay, ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, ha-hu miba-ye lei l'ched-tanya, you need
it for what we taught in the ברייתא. braitah.
אילו נאמר קרבן במלח, ilu ne-emar korban ba-melach, if it had just
said all of your קרבן korban should be with salt and it
did not say מנחתך. minchatcha. Why does it say כל קרבן מנחתך,
kol korban minchatcha, all of your מנחה mincha קרבנות korbanot you should
תמלח מלח timlach melach if we if we say that salt is
something we put on all of the קרבנות? korbanot? Okay, so why
did the תורה Torah emphasize it by the מנחה? mincha? For the
following
reason. אילו נאמר קרבן במלח, ilu ne-emar korban ba-melach, just your קרבן
korban with
salt, שומע אני אפילו עצים ודם, shome-a ani afilu etzim ve-dam, maybe
even when you bring wood and you burn wood, maybe even the
sprinkling of the blood which is called a קרבן. korban. We'll discuss
in a minute where it's called a קרבן. korban. תלמוד לומר מנחה,
talmud lomar mincha, no, that's why it uses מנחה mincha as the
paradigm. מה מנחה מיוחדת שאחרים באים חובה לה, ma mincha meyushedet she-acherim
ba-im chova lah, the same way מנחה mincha is distinct that other
things come with it as an obligation, so therefore אף כל שאחרים
באים חובה לו, af kol she-acherim ba-im chova lo, other things as
well that the מנחה mincha comes that other things come with it
as an obligation. Now what does this mean that other things come
with it as an obligation?
So it could mean, I'm sorry, not could mean, so the גמרא
Gemara is going to say that what it means is is that
you burn it on the fire. That when you take any קרבן
korban that you put on the fire, you need something else to
in order to bring the קרבן, korban, you need the wood. Okay,
it's a funny read of that שאחרים באים חובה לה, she-acherim ba-im
chova lah, but okay, you need the wood. So the same way
when you burn the קומץ kometz of the מנחה, mincha, not the
קטורת, ketoret, excuse me, the קומץ kometz of the מנחה, mincha, you
need wood, so therefore when you burn the what do you call
it, when you any time you're going to put something on the
fire, something that needs wood, that's when you need to have salt,
but not things that are not put on the fire. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to basically say that מנחה mincha is a
paradigm of things that you burn. So anything that you burn you
need salt, things you don't burn you don't need salt. And that's
going to be the basic principle. Now where do I know that
דם dam is what do you call it, that דם dam is
called a קרבן? korban? So there's not really a פסוק pasuk that
דם dam is called a קרבן, korban, but because the קרבן korban
is a fundamental part of the קרבן korban is דם, dam, the
גמרא Gemara takes it for granted that the same way דם, dam,
you know, atones and is a central part, the name קרבן korban
would apply to דם dam as well. How about wood? Where do
I know wood is called a קרבן? korban? The גמרא Gemara is
going to say it later, but it quotes a פסוק pasuk on
the עמוד ב amud bet if you want to look, a פסוק
pasuk from נחמיה, Nechemiah, it's a very small עמוד ב amud bet
so it shouldn't be too hard to find. And the פסוק pasuk
says והגורלות הפלנו על קרבן העצים. ve-ha-goralot hipallnu al korban ha-etzim.
So it calls it a קרבן korban of wood. Okay, so that's
why we had a question. Now we're going to discuss that in
a minute that a person can donate wood and bring wood as
a type of a קרבן. korban. But since you don't burn wood
on other wood, you actually burn the wood instead, so that would
be something that's on the fire but also is not like the
מנחה mincha because it's not burnt on other wood, it's just directly
burnt. Okay, so that's our principle. What needs salt? Anything like the
קומץ kometz that you burn. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues, the ברייתא braitah continues. מה מנחה מיוחדת שאחרים באים חובה לה
ma mincha meyushedet she-acherim ba-im chova lah אף כל שאחרים באים חובה
לו. af kol she-acherim ba-im chova lo. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, אי מה מנחה מיוחדת שמתרת אף כל שמתיר. ei ma
mincha meyushedet she-materet af kol she-matir. One minute, there's a more obvious
characteristic of the קומץ. kometz. What does the קומץ kometz do? It's
the מתיר matir of the מנחה. mincha. So let me say that
every קרבן, korban, every time you bring the מתיר matir you have
to salt it. So what would you salt by an animal קרבן?
korban? If you focus on the things you burn, what are you
going to salt by an animal קרבן? korban? What do you
burn? אימורים, imurim, and if it's an עולה, olah, the meat. If
you focus on the something that functions like the קומץ, kometz, so
something that's a מתיר, matir, you're going to burn you're going to
salt the דם. dam. So how do I know which aspect to
focus on if the paradigm is the קומץ? kometz? Do I focus
on the fact that it's burnt or do I focus on the
fact that it's a מתיר? matir? So let's take a look. Where
are we? יכול תהא מנחה מיוחדת שמתרת אף כל שמתיר, yakhol te-hei
mincha meyushedet she-materet af kol she-matir, אבי דם שמתיר, avi dam she-matir,
let me include blood. תלמוד לומר מעל מנחתך ולא מעל דמך. talmud
lomar mei'al minchatecha velo mei'al damecha. Now, it
says from your מנחה, mincha, right? It says מנחה mincha twice. First
it says וכל קרבן מנחתך vechol korban minchatecha and then it says
מנחת minchat a second time, מעל מנחתך. mei'al minchatecha. So it's saying
it's not enough that it's similar to one characteristic, meaning you can't
say, like, okay, take your choice: either things you burn or things
that are מתיר. matir. No, מעל מנחתך mei'al minchatecha says you only
some things we're including that are similar to מנחה, mincha, not others.
Now, it doesn't tell you which characteristic to focus on. You could
still say focus on the מתיר matir characteristic and not the burnt
characteristic. So the גמרא Gemara will get to that. But the basic
point is, yes, there are a lot of things you could compare
to מנחה mincha in different ways. The repetition of מנחה mincha is
telling us that it has to be only similar to מנחה mincha
in one particular way. And we're assuming that that particular way is
something that is burnt. Okay, so let's take a look. יכול תהא
מנחה כולה טעונה
מלח, yachol tehei mincha kula te'una melach, maybe it's the entire מנחה,
mincha, even the stuff that you eat, not just the stuff that
you burn? תלמוד לומר קרבן. talmud lomar korban. The stuff that is
קרב, karev, that is actually offered. קרבן טעון מלח, korban ta'un melach,
what is offered needs מלח, melach, ואין מנחה כולה טעונה מלח, ve'ein
mincha kula te'una melach, and not the entire מנחה. mincha. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, and it's actually the ברייתא, Braita, ואין לי
אלא קומץ, ve'ein li ela kometz, I only know the קומץ. kometz.
מנין לרבות את הלבונה, minayin lerabot et halevona, how do I include
the לבונה? levona? Now, the גמרא Gemara is going to want to
take apart this ברייתא Braita says, what do you mean? I just
got through saying that I can include anything that is burnt on
the מזבח. mizbeach. So of course I'm going to include the לבונה.
levona. Now why are you now doubling back and saying how do
I know the לבונה? levona? So we'll see the גמרא Gemara asks
that. But okay, now that I've said you burn the קומץ kometz
and anything like it, how do I know the לבונה? levona? מרבה
אני את הלבונה שכן באה עמה בכלי אחד. marbe ani et halevona
sheken ba'a imah bikli echad. Oh, well that will certainly I'll include
with the קומץ kometz because, you know, it comes together in the
same vessel, certainly was sanctified together in the same vessel with the
rest of the מנחה. mincha. אבל מנין לרבות את הלבונה הבאה בפני
עצמה? aval minayin lerabot et halevona haba'a bifnei atzmah? How do you
know about לבונה levona that comes by itself, if somebody just donates
לבונה levona as a קרבן? korban? או לבונה הבאה בבזיכין, o levona
haba'a bevazichin, the לבונה levona that comes in those little bowls by
the לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim? הקטורת, haktoret, or when you burn the
קטורת? ktoret? This is fascinating. Who ever heard about this? When the
כהן kohen burns the קטורת ktoret inside the היכל, heichal, right, and
it's twice a day, the פיטום הקטורת pitum haktoret that we say,
you know, at שבת Shabbos or whatever, it's something that's being burnt.
You've got to sprinkle a little salt on it. Okay? And the
same with the לבונה. levona. מנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח, minchat kohanim
uminchat kohen mashiach, how about a מנחה mincha that doesn't have a
קומץ, kometz, that you burn in its entirety? The מנחה mincha of
a כהן kohen or of a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. כהן גדול
kohen gadol brings a מנחה mincha every day, half in the morning,
half in the afternoon. ומנחת נסכים, uminchat nesachim, a מנחה mincha that
comes of the wine, you know, that comes together with a free-will
קרבן. korban. אימורי חטאת ואימורי אשם, imurei chatat ve'imurei asham, the אימורין,
imurin, the entrails of a חטאת chatat and an אשם, asham, ואימורי
קדשי קדשים, ve'imurei kodshei kodashim, or the entrails of any קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. What other קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is there other than
a חטאת chatat and an אשם? asham? There's an עולה, olah, but
then that's not the אימורין, imurin, that's just the איברים. evarim. You
wouldn't single out the אימורין imurin because everything is burnt. So that's
a חטאת. chatat. So the only other קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim that
exists that you only are מקריב makriv the entrails is our famous
lambs of שבועות, Shavuos, the שתי הלחם shtei halechem which are זבחי
שלמי ציבור. zivchei shalmei tzibur. They get a lot of play. Okay,
so they are the other קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim that exist that
you only do the אימורין. imurin. ואימורי קדשים קלים, ve'imurei kodashim kalim,
or the אימורין imurin of קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, like a normal
שלמים. shlamim. ואיברי עולה, ve'eivrei olah, the limbs of an עולה, olah,
which are, right, the עולה olah is totally burnt. ועולת העוף, ve'olat
ha'of, or a bird עולה. olah. How do you know all these
things? How do you know that you add salt to them? All
of these are things that are burnt. מנין? minayin? תלמוד לומר על
כל קרבנך תקריב מלח, talmud lomar al kol korbanecha takriv melach, and
all of your קרבנות. korbanot. So basically, the פשט pshat of this
is you put salt on things that are burnt, not on blood,
even though blood is a מתיר. matir. Now, what's funny about it
is after it sort of first made that statement it has to
be similar to a מנחה, mincha, it went back and did the
whole לימוד limud again. Ah, I only know לבונה, levona, how do
I know other things? I mean, after it just went through and
said that things are based, have to be like a מנחה. mincha.
So that is one of the first things the גמרא Gemara asks.
Let's take a look. אמר מר. amar mar. So now we're going
to go back and break this up piece by piece. ואין לי
אלא קומץ, ve'ein li ela kometz, I only know a קומץ. kometz.
מנין לרבות את הלבונה, minayin lerabot et halevona, how do I know
to include the לבונה? levona? מרבה אני את הלבונה שכן באה עמה
בכלי אחד. marbe ani et halevona sheken ba'a imah bikli echad. Okay,
no, that I can take for granted, it comes in the same
vessel. But how do I know all these other things? So says
the גמרא, Gemara, והאמרת, veha'amart, you said in the beginning of this
ברייתא, Braita, מה מנחה מיוחדת שכן באה חובה לה? mah mincha meyucheres
sheken ba'ah chova lah? A מנחה mincha you learned, you know, has
the distinct characteristic that other things come because of it, which means
that as the גמרא Gemara will explain, means that it's burnt on
a fire. So now that you've said that we learn that out
from a מנחה, mincha, why do you have to double back and
learn it all out again? So the גמרא Gemara says, הכי קאמר.
hachi ka'amar. No, here's why the ברייתא Braita doubled back. אימא קרבן
כלל ומנחה פרט כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. eima korban
klal umincha prat klal uprat ein baklal ela mah shebaprat. So what
the ברייתא Braita is saying is like this: I first learn out
it has to be similar to a מנחה mincha from the word
מנחה, mincha, but. You're going to come back and say to me,
don't say קרבן korban and מנחה, mincha, it means any קרבן korban
like a מנחה mincha and we let it be a broader statement
that it's enough that it's something that's burnt. You'll say to me,
why don't I say קרבן korban is a כלל, klal, מנחה mincha
is a פרט, prat, and it's only מנחה mincha and nothing else?
Okay, I mean actually פשט הפסוקים pshat hapsukim you'd read the פסוקים,
psukim, על כל קרבנך תקריב מלח. al kol korbankha takriv melach. First
it says כל קרבן מנחתך במלח תמלח kol korban minchatcha bamelach timlach
ולא תשבית מלח ברית אלהיך מעל מנחתך velo tashbit melach berit eloheicha
me'al minchatcha על כל קרבנך תקריב מלח. al kol korbankha takriv melach.
So actually the פסוקים, psukim, it's all מנחה, mincha, מנחה, mincha, מנחה,
mincha, and then the last phrase is כל קרבנך. kol korbankha. But
anyway, maybe I would have said that since there's an emphasis on
מנחה, mincha, מנחה mincha is the פרט prat and only מנחה mincha
and not anything like a מנחה. mincha. So you would have said
that, אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט, ein baklal ela mah shebaprat, מנחה
mincha אין, in, only a מנחה mincha gets salt, מידי אחרינא לא,
midi achrina lo, nothing else. So then the גמרא, Gemara, והדר אמר,
v'hadar amar, that's why the ברייתא Braitah continues to say, על כל
קרבנך תקריב מלח, al kol korbankha takriv melach, right, that was the
last part of the פסוק pasuk quoted, the last פסוק pasuk quoted
in the ברייתא. Braitah. חזר וכלל, chazar ve'chalal, so that's a general
statement and it's not limiting itself to מנחה. mincha. כלל ופרט וכלל
אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. klal u'prat u'klal ee ata dan
ela ke'ein haprat. So now, even though מנחה mincha is specific, you
have a general word in the beginning, קרבן מנחתך, korban minchatcha, and
then you have כל קרבנך kol korbankha at the end. מה הפרט
מפורש שהן באין חובה לה, mah haprat meforash shehen ba'in chovah lah,
so the same way מנחה mincha is distinct that other things come
because of it, meaning that you put wood on the fire and
it's burnt, אף כל שהן באין חובה לה, af kol shehen ba'in
chovah lah, also other things. So if you think about it, what,
you know, normally כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal is not necessarily
פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. Sometimes it is. For example, by
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni when the תורה Torah says, ונתת הכסף בכל
אשר תאוה נפשך בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך ואכלת
שם לפני ה' אלהיך. venatata hakesef bechol asher te'aveh nafshecha babakar uvatzon
uvayayin uvashachar uvechol asher tishalcha nafshecha ve'achalta sham lifnei Hashem eloheicha. So
what would you say פשט pshat is? You certainly wouldn't say just
the פרט. prat. You might say there are no limits, but on
the other hand, you would say, well why does it say everything
and then it gives examples? Presumably some things are excluded. So that's
like the normal logic of כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u'prat u'klal. And
that actually fits to a certain degree by the מנחה. mincha. You
read these פסוקים psukim and first they say מנחה, mincha, מנחה, mincha,
מנחה, mincha, right? כל קרבן מנחתך במלח תמלח kol korban minchatcha bamelach
timlach ולא תשבית מלח ברית אלהיך מעל מנחתך. velo tashbit melach berit
eloheicha me'al minchatcha. And then it says, על כל קרבנך. al kol
korbankha. So על כל קרבנך al kol korbankha obviously means everything, but
if it really meant everything, why emphasize מנחה? mincha? So here's where
כלל ופרט klal u'prat really makes sense in that it means everything
that is pretty much like a מנחה, mincha, everything that's burnt. At
least that's the characteristic that the גמרא Gemara focuses on. Okay, so
it's that it's burnt and not that it's a מנחה. mincha. So
now let's take a look at the specifics. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. שהן באין חובה לה מאי ניהו? shehen ba'in chovah
lah mai nihu? What does it mean other things come as an
obligation to it? So, עצים. etzim. So that's what I've been telling
you. It means wood, that you have to bring wood so that
you can burn it. And therefore we exclude something like blood, which
is not burnt, and we exclude wood, which is burnt, but it's
not burnt on other wood. אף כל עצים, af kol etzim,
so anything else that you need to bring wood and you need
to burn it on wood. So the גמרא Gemara says אימא, eima,
why not say, there's a question again of the גרסא, girsa, but
why didn't I, why not say מאי ניהו לבונה? mai nihu levona?
Why don't I say like this? No, no, no,
I'll take שהן באין חובה לה shehen ba'in chovah lah and read
it extremely narrowly. And maybe, or maybe I'll also read it in
the following way. It doesn't mean something that you have to burn
on a fire. It means when anything comes combined with it. What
comes combined with a מנחה? mincha? What do you bring together with
a מנחה? mincha? לבונה. levona. So what am I going to get
by saying focusing on the idea that מנחה mincha has things coming
with it, not only wood but even a לבונה? levona? It'll allow
me to say I should apply the salt to something else. What
am I going to put the salt on? ואייתי דם דאיכא נסכים.
v'ayti dam d'ika nesachim. And then I'll say, ah, now I'm going
to say that I will put salt on the blood because blood,
although it's not burnt, has something coming with it. What comes with
the blood? What comes with the blood is you also whenever you
sprinkle the blood, not whenever, but when for a free-will sacrifice when
you sprinkle the blood on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, something else comes along
with the blood. What comes along? The נסכים, nesachim, the you know,
the flour and the oil and the wine. And therefore they're conceptually
are they with the blood? Not clear. The גמרא Gemara will talk
about it, but it certainly comes with the קרבן. korban. So therefore
since it has something coming with it, why don't I say I
put salt on? So again, what's the גמרא's Gemara question? The גמרא
Gemara established that מנחה mincha is distinct, that it's burnt, so I
put salt on anything that is burnt. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, why only read it that way? Why not also say
since the way we got this idea of burnt was saying things
come with it, which means you burn it on wood, say by
blood also things come with it. What comes with? The oil and
the flour and therefore you will also put salt on the blood.
Okay, so let's take a look about what the גמרא Gemara does
with this. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, נסכים בהדי אימורין
הוא דאתו. nesachim bahadi emurin hu de'atu. The נסכים nesachim are not
connected to the blood; they're connected
to
the אימורין, emurin, the entrails that you
put on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. and you burn that as well. So, if I wanted
to say where am I going to group the נסכים, nesachim, presumably
would you group it conceptually with the blood or would you group
it with אימורין? imurin? Presumably, you'd group it with אימורין, imurin, right?
Because you'd say these are things that you put on the מזבח
mizbayach to burn on the מזבח. mizbayach. It's true that the wine
you don't burn, or actually there are some opinions that you do,
but anyway maybe you pour it down a funnel, but anyway you
do these things at the top of the מזבח mizbayach as opposed
to the blood. So, that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Don't
tell me blood needs salt because the נסכים nesachim come with blood;
the נסכים nesachim conceptually go together with the אימורין imurin and they
don't come together with the blood. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? So I was just focusing where
it was done, but the גמרא, Gemara, this is a fascinating גמרא
Gemara in terms of how it's thinking about קרבנות. korbanot. What's the
reason I would group the נסכים nesachim with the אימורין? imurin? אכילה
ושתיה. achila u-shtiya. Because the מזבח mizbayach has to eat and it's
got to drink. So therefore it eats the entrails, right, and it
drinks the wine that you pour on it. So now, that's a
lot more anthropomorphic than normally makes us comfortable, but it is pretty
honest with the פסוקים, psukim, you know, that calls the קרבנות korbanot
לחם אשה, lechem isheh, you know, לחם אשה. lechem isheh.
What? שלחן גבוה. shulchan gavoah. שלחן גבוה, shulchan gavoah, and it's my
bread and my meat and so on. So, they're saying that if
that's the concept, so if this is the meat of the מזבח,
mizbayach, this is the drink of the מזבח mizbayach and it's conceptually
linked with that. We don't say the מזבח mizbayach is drinking the
blood, but we could say that it's eating the אימורין imurin and
it's drinking, as it were, the wine. So that's how it's linked.
So the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, aderaba, no let me say the
opposite. כפרה ושמחה. kapara v-simcha.
Since the blood atones, so with atoning comes joy, and wine brings
joy. So if I wanted to link the wine, I would link
it with the blood because one affects the atonement and the other
is the joy that sort of, you know, gives the context for
the atonement. Now, I want to say two things about this. First
of all, that's interesting, maybe a little jarring for us. When we
think about atonement we normally think about the whole difficult process leading
up to it, you know, and not so much the aftermath and
we wouldn't normally say that I connect the idea of joy with
it. But that is the after, you know, which is why by
the way on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know, it says לא
היו ימים טובים בישראל כט"ו באב וכיום הכיפורים, lo hayu yamim tovim
b'Yisrael k'Tu B'Av u-k'Yom HaKippurim, right? Normally we don't associate joy with
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but if you focus on the fact that
you will get atonement and after you've gotten atonement, you know, you
do associate joy with it. Why we often wait to do, you
know, ברכת לבנה Birkat Levana till מוצאי יום כיפור. Motzaei Yom Kippur.
There's this idea of joy and we know that we were מכפר.
mechaper. So that's one thing that is interesting. The other thing that's
interesting is that it doesn't make sense because you only bring a
מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim with free will קרבנות. korbanot. You don't bring
it with a חטאת chatat and אשם. asham. You only bring it
with an עולה olah or שלמים. shlamim. Now, it's true that sometimes
you could bring an עולה olah for like מצות עשה mitzvot aseh
or whatever, but normally an עולה olah and שלמים shlamim are not
things we associate with the concept of כפרה. kapara. And anyway you
could say if it was about the שמחה simcha of כפרה kapara
you would bring it with a חטאת, chatat, and you don't bring
it with a חטאת. chatat. So it's a fascinating גמרא Gemara that
it wants to make this argument. God's שמחה? simcha?
No, yours, that you are getting atonement.
At least that's the way רש"י Rashi says. I understand why you're
suggesting what you are because what do you call it? Because it's
similar to the idea of אכילה ושתיה achila u-shtiya which is from
God's perspective. Yeah, but רש"י Rashi says it's yours. And רש"י Rashi
says,
well
actually
רש"י Rashi says המשמח אלוהים ואנשים, ha-mesameach Elokim va-anashim, I mean he's
quoting a פסוק, pasuk, דמי שנתכפר חטאו שמח, d'mi she-nitkaper chato sameach,
but then he focuses on the person. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says maybe I'll link it with the blood. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא לבונה באה עמה בכלי אחד נסכים אין באין בכלי אחד.
ella levona ba'ah imah b'kli echad nesachim ein ba'in b'kli echad. No,
I never would have included blood. Even if I would have said
that באה עמה ba'ah imah means not just the wood, but that
the לבונה levona other parts of the קרבן korban come with the
קומץ, kometz, and I would have said other things come with the
blood, you bring נסכים nesachim with the blood. If even if I
would have conceptualized it that way, I still would have said that
no because it's not as tightly linked as the לבונה levona is
to the קומץ. kometz. So there's no way I would have gotten
blood in the back door by focusing on the קומץ kometz לבונה
levona relationship. אבל עצים כי היכי דמתקשרא בהו מנחה הכי מתקשרא בכולהו
קרבנות. aval etzim ki heichi d'mitkashra behu mincha hachi mitkashra b'chulhu korbanot.
But when I want to say "comes with" does not mean the
לבונה, levona, but "comes with" means burnt on wood, then there's nothing
that is makes מנחה mincha more of a close connection to wood
than other קרבנות. korbanot. The same way you burn the מנחה mincha
on the wood, the קומץ kometz you burn other things on the
wood, and that allows me to include everything that's included in wood.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying is this idea is something comes
with, we can't focus on the לבונה. levona. The לבונה levona is
very tightly connected to the קומץ. kometz. You don't have that by
other קרבנות. korbanot. It would not allow us to expand outward anywhere
and not to the blood either. But we're going to say "comes
with" means it's put on the wood, therefore we apply it to
everything that's burnt, we don't apply it to the blood which is
not burnt. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. By
the way, it's fascinating that in this question the גמרא Gemara never
suggested the מנחה minchah part of the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. It
only suggested the wine part of the מנחת נסכים, Minchat Nesachim, presumably
because maybe wine and blood are both liquids, it saw them going
together, or this idea of שמחה, simcha, but presumably it assumed that
the מנחה minchah part of the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim goes with
the אימורים eimurim and is not connected to the blood. All right,
but anyway.
The קמיצה kemitza you're saying?
No, no, no. Every קרבן עולה korban olah or שלמים, shelamim, free
will, you bring with it a type of a מנחה, minchah, a
mix of wine and flour of oil and flour plus wine, and
you burn that on the—burn the wine and flour on the מזבח
mizbeach and you, you know, and you pour the wine. Okay, so
it's just interesting when it tries to argue things come with blood,
it focused on the wine and not on the—and you
instead of get קמיצה kemitza you burn the whole מנחה. minchah.
Yeah, exactly. Okay.
Now, so now the גמרא Gemara back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
so that's what we say that anything that you put on wood,
like a מנחה, minchah, is going to require
salt. ואימא, ve'eima, why don't I say מה פרט מפורש שהם באים
חובה לה ומתרת, ma prat meforash shehem ba'im chova la umateret, why
don't I say that it needs two points of similarity to the
מנחה? minchah? It has to be both burnt and, like the קומץ,
kometz, מתיר matir the rest of the קרבן. korban. Okay, so what
is that going to include? אף כל שהם באים חובה לה ומתרת.
af kol shehem ba'im chova la umateret. What other thing both is
burnt and is מתיר? matir? Not the blood, that's מתיר matir without
being burnt. Okay, not let's say a מנחת כהנים, minchat Kohanim, that's
fully burnt, but it's not מתיר. matir. The only other thing that
is both מתיר matir and burnt is the, ah, the לבונה levonah
of the מנחה minchah and the לבונה levonah of
the, uh, the—the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Okay, so ומאי ניהו לבונה
הבאה בבזיכין, umai nihu levonah haba'ah bebazichin, the לבונה levonah that comes
with those bowls, דשריא לחם, desharya lechem, that that's a מתיר matir
and it's burnt. אבל מידי אחריני לא, aval midi achrinei lo, nothing
else would require salt. So the גמרא Gemara says no. מדי איצטריך
מעל מנחתך ולא מעל דמך, midei itztarich me'al minchatecha velo me'al damecha,
since we needed an explicit פסוק pasuk to exclude blood based on
the earlier דרשה, drasha, מכלל דהנך כולהו אתו בחד צד. michlal dehanach
kulehu atu bechad tzad. If you had learned from מנחה minchah that
you needed two points of comparison, then I wouldn't have thought that
it was a big category that I need narrowing, and the only
other thing it would have included would have been one thing in
the universe, the לבונה. levonah. Since the way the דרשות drashot worked
before, we first assumed that it was a broad category, and then
you needed מעל מנחתך me'al minchatecha to tell us don't make it
too broad, tells me that the way I am comparing things that
are similar in even one aspect to a מנחה, minchah, they don't
need two characteristics, burnt and מתיר. matir. If that were true, it
would never have been too broad, because it started too broad, clearly
it was only—I assumed only one characteristic. So even after the פסוקים
psukim limit it, I'm not going to say you need two, I'm
just going to say only one specific characteristic, not any characteristic, only
one specific one. Which specific one? Not the מתיר, matir, that's not
what's relevant. What's relevant here is the fact that it is burnt.
Okay, now you have to admit again that that works well, because
the פסוקים psukim do make it sound by the end, על כל
קרבנך תקריב מלח, al kol korbanecha takriv melach, that it's a large
group. And therefore, if it was just about the salt—the blood and
was just focusing on the מתיר, matir, it would not be such
a large group. Also, תוספות Tosafot says that—I think תוספות Tosafot in
one of these contexts, תוספות Tosafot said that one of the reasons
we're inclined to assume that you put it on the meat and
the entrails, etc., and not on the blood is well, why in
your own mind would you say, if I had to think which
way to compare it? I know that I put it on the
קומץ. kometz. So now where should I put it? Should I put
it on the blood, or should I put it on the meat
and the entrails, etc.? So תוספות Tosafot says well, can you think
why, just from a very prosaic perspective? Yeah. Meat. Well, because תוספות
Tosafot says, what do you salt? You salt meat, and those are
the type—and you maybe sometimes put salt on your bread, on your
מנחות. minchot. Those are things that you normally salt. You don't normally
salt blood. So therefore you salt meat to get the blood out.
Right. But you don't normally salt blood. So therefore that's why we're
inclined to read it in this way that includes those types of
things. A, it's a broad category, and B, those types of things
that I would anyway normally salt. Okay, so let's take a look.
That's only because we don't eat blood.
You think if you ate blood, you put salt on it?
It's salty already. What? What's the recipe for—for—?
I don't know. Some people like—I mean, some people have those, what
do you call it? Those, you know, V8s, those tomato juices that
have salt and spices in them. So maybe if you had real
blood, you'd put salt on it. I don't know, it's a good
point. Anyway, for Jews, we don't salt blood. We salt the meat
to get out the blood.
You salt it once it's already on the מזבח? mizbeach? What?
Right before you put it on. Okay. All right. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where are we? Oh, yeah, תוספות Tosafot is going to say it
in a minute. So let's take a look. אמר מר. Amar mar.
So now we go
back. אמר מר, Amar mar, מעל מנחתך— me'al minchatecha We'll compare it
to things that are burnt. So the גמרא Gemara says מכלל דהנך
כולהו אתו בחד צד. mikelal dehanach kulehu asu bechad tzad. I'm sorry
did I just read it? ולא מעל דמך. velo me'al damecha. ואימא
מעל מנחתך ולא מעל אבריך? ve'eima me'al minchasecha velo me'al evarecha?
Right, if I'm going to compare it to blood in one way,
why compare it to the מנחה mincha in one way, why compare
to things that are burnt and exclude blood, why don't I do
the reverse? Compare it to blood that's a מתיר matir and exclude
the אברים eivarim etc. and things that are burnt? So the גמרא
Gemara says מסתברא אברים הוו ליה לרבויי. mistavra evarim havu lei leribuyei.
You know, it makes more sense to include the limbs, why? שכן
אשנבט טמ"ע סימן. shekein Ashnavat Tamei siman.
Okay, this is going to be an acronym. These are the ways
in which a מנחה mincha is similar, the קומץ komets is similar
to the אברים eivarim and not to the blood. So what is
that? א- אחרים באים חובה לה. alef- acherim ba'im chova la. It's
burnt, which we said means things have to come because of it.
For example, you have to put what do you call wood on
the fire כמוה. kamosa. ש-
אשים כמוה. shin- ishim kamosa. They're both burnt, which is very similar
to אחרים באים חובה לה. acherim ba'im chova la. The difference is
wood itself. If you don't eat wood itself, you don't bring other
wood. Okay, so it's both burnt and it's burnt on something external
to it, other wood. Those are the first two ways it's similar
to the אברים, eivarim, the קומץ. komets. ב- בחוץ כמוה. beis- bachutz
kamosa. That you only do the קומץ komets and the אברים eivarim
on the outer מזבח. mizbeach. Blood you sometimes do on the inner
מזבח, mizbeach, so it's not the same. נ- נותר כמוה. nun- notar
kamosa. Which you are חייב נותר chayav notar for leaving over the
limbs and for leaving over the what do you call it
the קומץ, komets, and if you eat it you're חייב כרת. chayav
kares. You are not חייב נותר chayav notar for דם. dam. The
גמרא Gemara learns that out somewhere else. Although you can't זורק zorek
the דם dam if it's old, you're not חייב נותר. chayav notar.
ט- טומאה כמוה. tes- tuma kamosa. Okay, if you are טמא tamei
and you eat the limbs or you eat the קומץ, komets, you're
חייב chayav for טומאת אוכל קודש, tum'as ochel kodesh, חייב כרת. chayav
kares. The גמרא Gemara learns out that that does not apply to
דם, dam, I mean you're חייב כרת chayav kares anyway for דם,
dam, but you're not חייב chayav because of טמא. tamei. מ- מעילה
כמוה. mem- me'ila kamosa. You get מעילה me'ila for misusing the limbs
or the קומץ, komets, which also דם dam is excluded from מעילה.
me'ila. It's fascinating that דם dam is excluded from all these things.
We haven't seen that yet, but that is the case. So in
these, all these ways it's similar. So we did אשבנ"ט Ashbanat which
is right, אחרים, acherim, אשים, ishim,
בחוץ, bachutz, נותר, notar, טומאה, tuma, and מעילה. me'ila. Now we didn't
explain the א-. alef. So תוספות Tosafos says what about the א-?
alef? Because it says אשנב"ט טמא. Ashnavat Tamei. So you could have
just said, no no
no, the what?
No, it's not an extra. So you could have just said that
was a helpful acronym, because טמא tamei is something that you can
remember, so even though the א- alef is extra. But תוספות Tosafos
says no, the א- alef actually means אוכל כמוה. ochel kamosa. It's
food. You normally, this is what the תוספות Tosafos I was telling
you, you normally salt food, which is a מנחה mincha and the
אברים, eivarim, you don't normally salt blood.
No, he
says it's not there because it's normally we say things that are
like חומרות chumros or קולות. kulos. That's just an interesting characteristic but
it's a relatively neutral one.
Okay, and most of these things that we say don't apply to
דם dam are simply because אימא ואמר אורי עליי... eima ve'amar ureh
alai...
oh you mean אין איסור חל על איסור? ein issur chal al
issur? No,
it's a special exception. I mean when we get to the דם
dam case we'll see it, but that's not what it's based on,
it's based on specific פסוקים pesukim that it's excluded. So the גמרא
Gemara says אדרבה דם הוי ליה לרבויי שכן מתיר כמוה. aderaba dam
havi lei leribuyei shekein matir kamosa. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, blood is similar to the מנחה. mincha. How is blood similar
to the מנחה? mincha? Number one, it's a מתיר, matir, right? When
the דם dam is מתיר matir the קרבן, korban, the קומץ komets
is מתיר matir the מנחה. mincha. And נפסל בשקיעת החמה כמוה. nifsal
beshki'as hachama kamosa. When you leave over, when it becomes שקיעה, shki'ah,
the blood becomes, you can't be זורק zorek the blood, and you
can't be מקטיר maktir the קומץ. komets. But what's the הלכה halacha
about the אברים eivarim that you're supposed to burn on the מזבח?
mizbeach? You can burn them כל הלילה. kol halaylah. Things that you're
supposed to burn that are not מתירים matirim you can burn כל
הלילה kol halaylah once you've done the מתיר. matir. The מתיר matir
has to be done in the day, the קומץ komets or the
blood, and then you can burn the stuff on the מזבח mizbeach
כל הלילה. kol halaylah. Okay, so that's another way in which blood
is similar. תוספות Tosafos asks there's yet another way, blood and קומץ
komets cannot become פיגול pigul because you're a מתיר. matir. You right?
פיגול pigul is only the stuff that's left over, not the not
the thing that's the מתיר matir itself. So actually what it's saying
is
all these are aspects of being a מתיר. matir. Because it's a
מתיר matir it has to be during the day as opposed to
after the מתיר matir then you can burn stuff later at night.
Because it's a מתיר matir it is a מתיר, matir, that's what
it said, and you could have thrown in פיגול pigul it doesn't
become פיגול pigul because it's a מתיר. matir. Anyway these are ways
in which it's similar. The גמרא Gemara says nevertheless הנך נפישן. hanach
nefishan. Alright, but you know we had a much bigger list for
the comparison of the קומץ komets to other things that are burnt,
so that's what we're going to emphasize. So in the end מנחה
mincha is the paradigm for things that are burnt and not the
paradigm for מתיר matir and anything that is burnt is what you
put salt on. Okay now why by the way this גמרא Gemara
seems pretty straightforward why Why by the way do we have this
huge תוספות Tosfos which we will find because we're a little behind
on the דף, daf, because we have such a big תוספות Tosfos
we will finish in time God willing. Why is there a huge
תוספות Tosfos here? It has very little to do with what we
said, but it has a lot to do להלכה lehalacha because the
גמרא Gemara says here that the דם dam is נפסל בשקיעת החמה.
nifsal bishkias hachama.
And תוספות Tosfos uses this as an opportunity to discuss the position
of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that says that
לילה layla starts not like what the גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbos
says, three quarters of a מיל mil after sunset, which is about
13, 15 minutes after sunset, but לילה layla starts based on a
גמרא Gemara in פסחים, Pesachim, four מיל mil after sunset, 72 minutes.
Okay, so רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam own position actually allowed for not
only being strict that after שבת Shabbos you have to wait for
72 minutes, but it allowed for leniencies as well because he basically
said that it's not even בין השמשות bein hashmashos until close to
an hour after visible sunset. Okay, people nowadays that rule like רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam rule him לחומרא. lechumra. I mean, you'll almost never
find anybody that will go לקולא lekula and rely on him for
anything after sunset itself. What was he based on? He's based on
the fact that the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim says it takes
72— that the traveling of the sun through the thickness of the
רקיע rakia is four מיל, mil, 72 minutes, because the גמרא Gemara
believes that you had— the world was created basically on a flat
world and a thick opaque רקיע rakia over it like this, except
it was more of a dome than a teepee, but I don't
have— I only have this. Anyway, the sun, right, rose in the
east and set in the west. Okay, sorry I didn't set that
up, but anyway, here, something like this, right? The sun rose in
the east and set in the west. Now, after sunset, there was
still some light. Why? Because the sun was traveling through a window
here in this thickness of this רקיע, rakia, right, it was traveling
through, so some light was still escaping and why you still see
light after sunset. And then, when it went through the entire thickness
and it got to the other side, it traveled above there at
night, which is why it's dark at night, okay, and why you
don't see it. And then it starts getting light before sunrise because
it's coming through the thickness here. Okay, so that's how the גמרא—
Gemara the גמרא's Gemara astronomy. And the גמרא Gemara says the thickness
was four מיל. mil. So רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says it is
not בין השמשות bein hashmashos as soon as the sun starts traveling
through the thickness, it's only בין השמשות bein hashmashos when it gets
towards the end of that thickness and is about to sort of
start rising. So you have close to an hour after visible sunset
until בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. Anyway, he says this to reconcile contradictory
גמרות Gemoros and the reason תוספות Tosfos elaborates on it here is
because
by קרבנות korbanos there are two פסוקים. pesukim. Once the גמרא Gemara
says a פסוק pasuk is you have to do everything when it's
still day, and then the גמרא Gemara quotes another פסוק pasuk that
you have to be מקריב makriv when it's still day. You have
to sort of be— so תוספות Tosfos says why do you need
two פסוקים? pesukim? So רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam explains that by קרבנות
korbanos we go by the first sunset, we go by the visible
sunset, and that's why you needed two פסוקים pesukim by קרבנות. korbanos.
But by normal הלכה, halacha, right, so the end of the day
for קרבנות korbanos would be the visible sunset. But by normal הלכות,
halachos, like by שבת Shabbos and whatever, you go by the second
sunset. Anyway, that's to give you a sense of what this huge
תוספות Tosfos is doing here. He's trying to elaborate on the position
of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that בין השמשות bein hashmashos and לילה
layla is really from this second sunset, close to an hour after
the visible one, but by קרבנות korbanos we would go by mostly
by the first sunset, which is— so he's all this is on
this thing about נפסל בשקיעת החמה. nifsal bishkias hachama. Okay? So just
so you understand why we have a shorter דף daf today and
it's a very central תוספות Tosfos in הלכות halachos of day and
night. Let's continue back in the גמרא. Gemara.
תוספות Tosfos era science recognized that this position of the גמרא Gemara
was wrong
and he's keeping it because it's חז"ל Chazal or he keeps— Good
question.
Is it that— no, sometimes people say by science issues, there's a
whole discussion, do you revise הלכה halacha because of— when science changes
and so on? But and sometimes for people that are at, very
sort of conservative-minded, they'll say, 'Oh well you never know the הלכה
halacha was really based on this belief of science, maybe it was
really, maybe it was based on other things and the science was
just a post-facto explanation.' So you can't change הלכה halacha just because
science changes. Now, normally I'm skeptical— I'm not talking about whether you
change הלכה halacha now, but I'm skeptical to say that it was
a post-facto explanation when it sounds like it was the real explanation.
But when the גמרא's Gemara talking about day or
night, in my mind, I don't see why we should assume that
it was defining it based on this particular astronomical belief. Meaning, the
גמרא Gemara is also looking around itself, the people— the חז"ל Chazal
are looking around and saying, 'Is it still light? Is it dark?
At what time?' especially if the definition of night is צאת הכוכבים,
tzeis hachochavim, which is when the stars come out and when it
gets fully dark and so on. So here I really do believe
that the astronomical explanation was not the source of saying that this
is night and
day, it was what was assumed, but they were basically referring to
the degree of darkness. But there are some that want to— suggest
that it is totally discounted. Oh, the point I did make is
the reason רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam was very inclined to read this
way, and it also was adopted by a number of different ראשונים,
Rishonim, even though it's not the most elegant resolution of the גמרא
Gemara and really is very much against a lot of פשט pshat
is because in France, which is a high
latitude, right, it gets it's very light even after sunset, and it
only gets dark, has anybody ever been in Israel? Right, which is
only a few degrees latitude, right, south of where we are in
New York, right, you know that it gets dark very, very quickly
after sunset, much more quickly than in New York, right, has anybody
noticed that? In ירושלים, Yerushalayim, like it seems like
it was an illusion.
No, it really is. It gets much darker much more quickly. And
you go to France, which is a even a little bit of
few degrees more high, it takes much longer to get dark. So
that influenced רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam read that.
So he starts שבת Shabbat very late?
According to what he says, he would start שבת Shabbat even an
even, you know, even up to 4, 50-some minutes after שקיעה. shkiah.
But there's nobody who starts שבת Shabbat late.
Everyone just holds it. Right, nowadays, nobody...
nowadays, nobody as a הלכה. halakha.
There are people who still don't do מלאכה, melacha, but they'll start
מנחה Mincha later after the זמן, zman, and they'll start davenen מעריב.
Ma'ariv.
שבת Shabbos ends very late in France in the summertime. Uh-huh.
Well, that's because even sunset is late. And but then even after
sunset, it's still light a good deal afterwards and that, you know,
that influences הלכה. halakha.
That's true in winter and summer?
I don't know. Okay, let's take a look. Now we are not
going to finish the דף. daf. אמר מר, Amar Mar, שומע אני
אפילו עצים ודם שנקראו קרבן, shome'a ani afilu etzim v'dam shenikru korban,
so maybe I would put salt on on the wood and the
blood, which are called a קרבן, korban, and then it says no,
because you don't burn them on wood. So מאן שמעת ליה דאמר
עצים איקרי קרבן, man shams ley d'amar etzim ikri korban, we'll have
to take for granted since it's the central part, it's called a
קרבן. korban. Where have I heard that wood is called a קרבן?
korban?
So, I'm sorry. Who is the one that says that wood is
called a קרבן? korban? רבי. Rebbi. רבי, Rebbi, as we'll see in
a minute, says wood is called a קרבן, korban, but לרבי מיבעי
בהו מלח, le-Rebbi miba vo melach, but רבי Rebbi says because it's
called a קרבן, korban, you do put salt on it. How do
we know this? דתניא: detanya: קרבן, korban, so this is a דרשה
drasha again on that פסוק, pasuk, מלמד שמתנדבים
עצים, melamed she-mitnadvim etzim, that you can donate wood as a
קרבן. korban. וכמה, v'khama, how much would you give? שני גזירין, shenei
gezerim, two logs. וכן הוא אומר, v'khen hu omer, והגורלות הפלנו על
קרבן העצים. v'hagoralot hipallnu al korban ha-etzim. So we cast lots regarding
this קרבן korban of the wood, so you see that they call
wood a קרבן. korban. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, עצים קרבן מנחה
הן. etzim korban mincha hen. Not only are they a קרבן korban
like you can donate wood to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but they actually
are a type of a מנחה. mincha. And what does this mean?
Now, by the way, that sounds a little bizarre, but we're gonna
find out that you can give לבונה levona as a מנחה, mincha,
you can give I mean you can give oil as a מנחה,
mincha, חז"ל Chazal take this concept of מנחה mincha and expand it
to other types of foods, and here according to רבי Rebbi even
wood that can be given as a מנחה mincha by itself. So
he says it's even a מנחה. mincha. What does this mean? וטעונים
מלח. v'te'unim melach. You put salt on it. וטעונים הגשה, v'te'unim hagasha,
and you have to do הגשה, hagasha, you have to touch it
to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you treat it like a real מנחה. mincha.
ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava, לדברי רבי, l'divrei Rebbi, עצים טעונים קמיצה. etzim
te'unim kmitza. You have to do קמיצה. kmitza. So which means you
have to chop off of some of the wood in order to
do קמיצה. kmitza. תוספות Tosafot says I don't get it. If you're
doing קמיצה kmitza but you're burning the rest of the wood anyway,
קמיצה kmitza is normally you burn part and you do something with
the rest. תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, but we have other examples where
you can do קמיצה kmitza and then you put up the rest
to burn as well. Okay, so it's a real קרבן. korban. ואמר
רב פפא, ve'amar Rappa, לדברי רבי, l'divrei Rebbi, עצים צריכים
עצים. etzim tzrichim etzim. According to רבי, Rebbi, wood needs wood, because
you have to burn it on something else. It's not that this
is actually just given as wood for the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's given
as a type of an offering. Now in something, there's something very
beautiful about this I must say, that you know, the whole idea
of מנחה mincha is somebody can't afford an animal, he gives something
more basic, sustenance, the flour, the wine, and now the oil, and
now חז"ל Chazal expand this to include a range of things that
people just want to give to God. So you even if all
you have is, you know, wood to give, you can give that
as an offering. And it's an offering that's put on the fire,
not that's burnt itself, but that's put on other wood.
You're making it more expensive by saying you need to add the
מלח melach and you need to add the...
First of all, that's a מקדש mikdash expense. They're not saying you
add לבונה. levona.
But the מלח melach is there... Yeah, the so the donor doesn't
bring...
No, presumably not. And anyway, and and that's the only thing that
you're adding, right? Everything else is a right, but it's not a
thing.
It's not as well with the thing for the... not מעכב me'akev
with the מנחה, mincha, right? Because you can't need wood, right? Right.
Oh, that's interesting. According to רבי Rebbi maybe that informs some of
the rest. That's interesting. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says alright, סמי
מכאן עצים, sami mikan etzim, take עצים etzim off the list. Now
of course, it's very bizarre why we have to take עצים etzim
off the list. חז"ל Chazal also say the חכמים chachamim that argue
at רבי Rebbi say you can give עצים, etzim, they just don't
treat it like a מנחה, mincha, right? But the but תוספות Tosafot
explains that since it says I might think עצים etzim need... needs
salt because עצים *etzim* are a קרבן *korban*, so the emphasis of
the ברייתא *baraita* that calls עצים *etzim* a קרבן *korban* really only
fits with רבי *Rabbi* that really gives it a full קרבן *korban*
status. Okay, although again, the simpler thing to say is that it's
going like the חכמים *Chachamim* against רבי *Rabbi*, that you can donate
it, and it's a קרבן *korban*, but it's not a מנחה *mincha*,
and therefore you don't put salt on it. So then the גמרא
*Gemara* ends, and with this we'll end: אלא קרא למיעוטי מאי *ela
kra leme'utei mai*? So at the end of the day, what am
I excluding of all the things you put salt on? What's the
only thing you don't put salt on? אי למיעוטי דם *i leme'utei
dam*, so if all it is is the blood, מעל מנחתך נפק
*me'al minchatecha nafak*. You exclude that from the פסוק *pasuk* מעל מנחתך
*me'al minchatecha* ולא מעל דמך *velo me'al damecha*. But we seem to
have excluded a set of things. So what are we excluding other
than blood? And the גמרא *Gemara* says, אפיק עצים ואייעל נסכים *afik
etzim ve'ayal nesachim*, and we'll pick up with this tomorrow. The only
other thing you exclude other than blood is the נסכים *nesachim*, not
the מנחת נסכים *minchat nesachim*, which is the flour and the oil
that you put salt on, but the wine that comes with קרבנות
*korbanot*, since you don't burn the wine, you pour the wine down
a funnel, so that's the other thing that you offer that is
not burnt. Blood and wine, two things that are, one is sprinkled,
the other is poured, and those are things that you do not
put salt on. Alright, to be continued tomorrow.